Miscellaneous letters collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Miscellaneous letters collection
1649-1961
Ms Coll 49
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
2
(4 boxes)
Miscellaneous Letters Collection is a collection of hundreds of individual letters or small groups of letters, mostly by physicians and scientists, either donated to the Historical Library or purchased.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains individual letters or small groups of letters from the correspondence of scientists, physicians, and other health practitioners. Provenences vary greatly. Some were donated by collectors or descendents of the recipient, others purchased, and others removed from books in the Historical Library in which collectors had placed them. Most letters were acquired in the period before 1960. Members of the Beaumont Medical Club collected and donated letters related to Connecticut medicine. John F. Fulton, in particular, purchased individual letters from book stores and book sellers for the collection. A number of the letters in the collection are to and from Yale School of Medicine faculty members. There are also some letters by Yale medical students and alumni. Of particular note in this collection are letters on inoculation and vaccination for smallpox, and on anesthesia.
Arrangement
Letters, with a few exceptions, are arranged alphabetically by author.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Anesthesia; Epidemics -- Connecticut; Electricity; Medical colleges; Medical education; Medical publishing; Medicine -- Connecticut; Medicine -- France; Medicine -- Great Britain; Medicine -- Societies, etc.; Medicine -- United States; Medicine, Military; Mental illness; Physiology; Psychiatric hospitals; Public health; Quacks and quackery; Rabies -- Vaccination; Resuscitation; Science -- Societies, etc.; Smallpox; Surgery; Typhus fever; Vaccination; Yellow fever; Correspondence; Physicians; Scientists; Ackland, A. A.; Acland, Henry W. (Henry Wentworth), 1815-1900; Addams, Charles, 1912-1988; Aiken, Arthur; Alison, William Pulteney, 1790-1859; Alsop, Charles Richard; Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943; Aschoff, L. (Ludwig), 1866-1942; Astruc, Jean, 1684-1766; Babinski, J. (Joseph), 1857-1932; Bache, Thomas Hewson, 1826-1912; Bacon, Francis, 1831-1912; Baillie, Matthew, 1761-1823; Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820; Barbauld, Mrs. (Anna Letitia), 1743-1825; Bartlett, Levi, 1763-1828; Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1888-1970; Beddoes, Thomas, 1760-1808; Bell, Charles, Sir, 1774-1842; Bergmann, M. (Max), 1886-1944; Bernard, Claude, 1813-1878; Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910; Blair, William; Blumenbach, Johann Friedrich, 1752-1840; Blumer, George, 1872-1962; Boerhaave, Herman, 1668-1738; Bogin, Maxwell, 1901-1997; Boissier de la Croix de Sauvages, François, 1706-1767; Boott, Francis, 1792-1863; Bostock, John, 1773-1846; Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691; Bradford, Thomas, 1745-1838; Bright, Richard, 1789-1858; Brown-Séquard, Charles-Edouard, 1817-1894; Bunting, Charles H., 1875-1961; Burggraeve, Ad. (Adolphe), 1806-1902; Butler, John Simpkins, 1803-1890; Buttner, J. L. (Jacques Louis), 1876-; Callow, W. J.; Calmette, A. (Albert), 1863-1933; Canning, Edward W. B. (Edward Weeks Boldero), 1813-1890; Canning, Josiah Weeks, 1780-1854; Cardwell, P. H.; Carmalt, William H. (William Henry), 1836-1929; Carter, Eugene; Chapman, Nathaniel, 1780-1853; Charcot, J. M. (Jean Martin), 1825-1893; Chambers, William Frederick, 1786-1855; Chase, Salmon P. (Salmon Portland), 1808-1873; Chastenet de Puységur, A.-M.-J. (Armand-Marie-Jacques), 1751-1825; Choulant, Ludwig, 1791-1861; Clark, J. A.; Clark, William; Cline, Henry, 1750-1827; Cobb, J. C.; Cogswell, James; Colladon, Jean Pierre, 1769-1842; Colton, G. Q. (Gardner Quincy), 1814-1898; Combe, George, 1788-1858; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; Coomes, Sexton P.; Cooper, Astley, Sir, 1768-1841; Corrigan, Dominic, Sir, 1802-1880; Crawford, Albert Beecher, 1891-; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Dam, H. (Carl Peter Henrik), 1895-1976; Darwin, Charles, 1758-1778; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Darwin, Erasmus, 1731-1802; Davy, Humphry, Sir, 1778-1829; Deleuze, J. P. F. (Joseph Philippe François), 1753-1835; Dexter, Franklin Bowditch, 1842-1920; D'Herelle, Félix; Dieulafoy, Georges, 1839-1911; Dindorf, Wilhelm, 1802-1883; Doremus, Robert Ogden, 1824-1906; Drake, Daniel, 1785-1852; Du Bois-Reymond, Emil, 1818-1896; Duckworth, Dyce, Sir, 1840-1928; Dunglison, Robley, 1798-1869; Dutrochet, Henri, 1776-1847; Ehrlich, Paul, 1854-1915; Elie de Beaumont, L. (Léonce), 1798-1874; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867; Ferrier, David, 1843-1928; Ferris, H. B. (Harry Burr), 1865-1940; Fischer, Emil, 1852-1919; Fischer, Hermann; Fitz, Reginald H. (Reginald Heber), 1843-1913; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854; Fothergill, Alexander; Fothergill, John, 1712-1780; Fothergill, LeRoy D. (LeRoy Dryden), 1901-1967; Francis, S. W.; Frank, Johann Peter, 1745-1821; Fry, Clements Collard, 1892-1955; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Galton, Francis, 1822-1911; Gardiner, Silvester, 1708-1786; Geikie, Archibald, 1835-1924; Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Etienne, 1772-1844; Gilbert, Solomon; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928; Gregg, Alan, 1890-1957; Guérin, Jules; Hale, M. (Moses); Haller, Albrecht von, 1708-1777; Halsted, William, 1852-1922; Hamilton, Alice, 1869-1970; Hart, Levi, 1738-1808; Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1886-1953; Haüy, Valentin, 1745-1822; Hawley, Joseph R. (Joseph Roswell), 1826-1905; Hayes, I. I. (Isaac Israel), 1832-1881; Helmholtz, Hermann von, 1821-1894; His, Wilhelm, 1831-1904; Hogg, Jabez, 1817-1899; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Hooker, Charles, 1799-1863; Horsley, Victor, Sir, 1857-1916; Howard, John, 1726-1790; Howell, William H. (William Henry), 1860-1945; Howitt, William, 1792-1879; Hubbard, Leverett; Hubbard, Thomas, 1776-1838; Hudson, W. H. (William Henry), 1841-1922; Hughes, Thomas; Humphry, George Murray, Sir, 1820-1896; Hunt, Reid, 1870-1948; Hunt, Willis Roberts, 1893-; Hunter, John, 1728-1793; Hurd, Henry M. (Henry Mills), 1843-1927; Ingalls, William, 1769-1851; Inouye, Takeo; Jamieson, Alexander; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jenner, Edward, 1749-1823; Jennings, Hargrave, 1817?-1890; Johnston, John, 1806-1879; Jones, Bence, 1814-1873; Jones, George; Jowett, Benjamin, 1817-1893; Keen, William W. (William Williams), 1837-1932; Keith, Arthur, Sir, 1866-1955; Kershaw, Richard; Keynes, Geoffrey, 1887-1982; Kingsbury, John Adams, 1876-1956; Kinne, Amassa Farrington; Klebs, Arnold C. (Arnold Carl), 1870-1943; Kneeland, Samuel, 1821-1888; Knight, J. (Jonathan), 1789-1864; Knighton, William, Sir, 1776-1836; Kronecker, Hugo, 1839-1914; La Condamine, Charles-Marie de, 1701-1774; Lane, John E.; Lankester, E. Ray, Sir (Edwin Ray), 1847-1929; Lewes, George Henry, 1817-1878; Litchfield, Henrietta Emma Darwin, 1843-1929; Long, C. N. H. (Cyril Norman Hugh), 1901-1970; Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891; Lu, Gwei-Djen; Luc, J. A. de (Jean André), 1727-1817; Lucchesini, Girolamo, 1751-1825; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Macaulay, James, 1817-1902; Macaulay, T. B.; Mackenzie, James, 1853-1925; Mailhouse, Max, 1857-1941; Malpighi, Marcello, 1628-1694; Malthus, T. R. (Thomas Robert), 1766-1834; Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1790-1852; Marcet, Alexander, 1770-1822; Marie, Pierre, 1853-1940; Martin, H. N.; McCormick, Harold; McFarland, Charles S.; Mease, James, 1771-1846; Mesmer, Franz Anton, 1734-1815; Messinger, William J.; Mills, Charles L.; Miltenberger, G. W. (George Warner), 1819-1905; Minkowski, Mieczyslaw, 1884-1972; Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914; Mivart, St. George Jackson, 1827-1900; Moffatt, Thomas, 1818-; Monsey, Messenger, 1693-1788; Moore, Norman, 1847-1922; Morgan, Charles F.; Morrison, Albert, 1820-1873; Mott, Valentine, 1785-1865; Müller, F. Max (Friedrich Max), 1823-1900; Musselman, Luther Kyner; Naegeli, Otto, 1871-1938; Neander, Gustaf Verner, 1874-1942; Needham, Joseph, 1900-1995; Nightingale, Florence, 1820-1910; Nightingale, Frances; Noyes, Burr; Odier, Louis, 1748-1817; O'Donaghue, Edward Geoffrey; Oliver, William, 1695-1764; Olmsted, Denison, 1791-1859; Osborne, Oliver T. (Oliver Thomas), 1862-1940; Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892; Paget, James, Sir, 1814-1899; Paine, Samuel, 1754-1807; Papaspyros, N. S. (Nikos S.); Parkman, George, 1790-1849; Pasteur, Louis, 1822-1895; Peaslee, E. R. (Edmund Randolph), 1814-1878; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948; Philippart, John, Sir; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; Powers, James, Capt.; Prescott, Benjamin T.; Prevost, Jean Louis, 1790-1850; Ramsay, David, 1749-1815; Remak, Robert, 1815-1865; Retzius, Gustaf, 1842-1919; Richardson, Maurice H.; Roberts, T. W.; Roget, Peter Mark, 1779-1869; Rolleston, Humphry Davy, Sir, 1862-1944; Roper, Laura Wood, 1911-2003; Rosencrantz, Esther, 1876-1950; Routh, Martin Joseph, 1755-1854; Ruggles, Arthur Hiler, 1881-1961; Sahli, Hermann, 1856-1933; Salter, William Thomas, 1901-1952; Sarton, George, 1884-1956; Sassoon, Ruby; Sawyer, Asa; Scales, William, 1741-1807; Selye, Hans, 1907-1982; Senn, Milton J. E., 1902-; Seymer, Lucy Ridgely; Seymour, George Dudley, 1859-1945; Sharpey, William, 1802-1880; Sherrington, Charles Scott, Sir, 1857-1952; Shiga, Kiyoshi, 1870-1957; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Simpson, James Young, 1811-1870; Singer, Charles, 1876-1960; Sloane, Hans, Sir, 1660-1753; Smith, Alexander; Smith, George H. (George Hathorn), 1885-1952; Smith, George Milton, 1879-1951; Smith, Herbert E. (Herbert Eugene), 1857-1933; Smith, J. Talcott; Smith, Nathan, 1762-1829; Smith, Nathan, 1770-1835; Smith, Nathaniel, 1762-1822; Spallanzani, Lazzaro, 1729-1799; Sperry, N. D.; Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle); Steele, H. D.; Steig, William, 1907-2003; Steiner, Walter Ralph, 1870-1942; Sternberg, George Miller, 1838-1915; Stewart, Charles H.; Streeter, Edward Clark, -1947; Sullivan, John L.; Swain, Henry Lawrence; Swieten, Gerard, Freiherr van, 1700-1772; Symington, Clark; Tennant, Charles J.; Tiedemann, Friedrich, 1781-1861; Tingry, P. F. (Pierre François), 1743-1821; Tissot, S. A. D. (Samuel Auguste David), 1728-1797; Torrey, John, 1796-1873; Turk, W.; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893; Tyson, James, 1841-1919; Vicq-d'Azyr, M. (Félix), 1748-1794; Vincent, H. (Hyacinthe), 1862-1950; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913; Warren, John, 1753-1815; Warren, Jonathan Mason, 1811-1867; Watkins, Samuel C. G., 1853-1942; Watkins, Tobias, 1780-1855; Weber, Frederick Parkes, 1863-1962; Weigert, Carl, 1845-1904; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934; Whipple, George Hoyt, 1878-1976; Wightman, Joseph M. (Joseph Milner), 1812-1885; Williams, Francis H. (Francis Henry), 1852-1936; Wilson, William C.; Winslow, C.-E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1877-1957; Winslow, Forbes, 1810-1874; Winternitz, M. C. (Milton C.), 1885-1959; Witherell, H. M.; Woodford, William; Woodruff, Timothy L. (Timothy Lester), 1858-1913; Woodward, Joseph Janvier, 1833-1884; Wright, Frank W.; Young, Thomas, 1773-1829; Zinsser, Hans, 1878-1940; Académie des sciences (France); Beaumont Medical Club; Connecticut Medical Society; Fairfield County Medical Association; New Haven County Medical Association; Rockefeller Foundation; Royal Society (Great Britain); University of Edinburgh; University of Oxford; Yale College (1718-1887); Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution; Yale University. School of Medicine; Cobb, J. C.
- Ackland, A. A., Silver Creek [Indiana?], to P. M. Barrows, Oberlin, Ohio, 1836 June 28 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  About the death of his patient and dear friend, Henry B. Clark. Letter contains a detailed case narrative.
  The letter was the gift of Sidney Withington in January 1959, whose wife was a descendent of the recipient.
- Acland, Henry W., to Mr. Gross, 1898 September 15 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 2)
  Henry Acland was Regius Professor of Medicine at Oxford to 1895. E. Ray Lankester left the Linacre professorship of comparative anatomy at Oxford in 1898 to become director of the British Museum. (Natural History). Letter by Henry Acland is to an unidentified recipient discussing raising funds for a public health building and the search for a successor to Lankester.
  The letter was removed from John Fulton's copy of Acland's Oxford and Modern Medicine, 1890.
- Addams, Charles, New York, to Clements C. Fry, two letters, 1944 October 16 - 1944 October 24 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 3)
  Concerning Fry's purchasing of drawings by Addams, a cartoonist for the New Yorker.
- Aiken, Arthur [London], to [James?] Asperne [London], 1818 June 25 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 4)
  Letter of Arthur Aikin on behalf of the Society of Arts to [James?] Asperne thanking him for portraits for the Society. Aikin does not have a portrait of himself to furnish but will be available if Mr. Drummond (an artist?) should call. Gift of L. Cohen, Argosy Books, 1952.
- [Alsop, Charles Richard] 5 letters to Charles R. Alsop, 1820-1839 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 5)
  Charles Richard Alsop graduated from Yale College in 1821 and practiced law in Middletown, Connecticut. The folder contaians letters to Charles Richard Alsop from his sister, Lucy Chauncey, his mother, and Charles Woodward of Middletown, Connnecticut, discussing a yellow fever scare attributed in part to Yale medical professor, William Tully, family matters, social life in Middletown, the illness and death of Lucy Chauncey's daughter, Clara, en route to Valparaiso, social life in Valparaiso where Lucy Chauncey settled with her family, quarantine of ships for cholera in Valparaiso, Alsop's engagement to Margaret Armstrong, and Mrs. Dana's eye problems. The letters were the gift of Mrs. Kenneth McKenzie, granddaughter of Charles Richard Alsop, 1956.
- American Laryngological Society, 2 letters to Henry L. Swain, New Haven, 1939 January 18 - 1939 June 30 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 6)
  Letters signed by James A Babbitt and Charles J. Imperatori, successive secretaries of the American Laryngological Association, concern Swain's election to Honorary Fellowship. Gift of Henry L. Swain.
- Andrews, Charles M., East Dover, Vermont, to John E. Lane, New Haven, 1933 October 15 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 7)
  Review of a book in French on French hospitals in the colonies from 1777 to 1784. Lane was interested in French physicians serving in the Revolutionary war.
- Aschoff, Ludwig, to Dr. Charles H. Bunting, 1921 November 9 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 8)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Charles H. Bunting, January 1953.
- Astruc, Jean, Toulouse, to "Monsieur", 1726 April 26 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 9)
  Letter of Jean Astruc to an unknown correspondent excusing his absence from an unnamed scientific society and presenting the society with a geometric problem transmitted by a geometer in the area. Removed from the Library's copy of Astruc, Mémoires pour servir a l'histoire de la Faculté de Médecine de Montpellier(1767).
- Babinski, Joseph, Paris, to [Edgar?] Berillon, 1892 July 2 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 10)
  Letter from Joseph Babinski to [Edgar?] Berillon thanking him for the invitation to the next meeting of the Societe d'Hypnologie. He has nothing to present but will attend. Gift of John F. Fulton, 1950.
- Baillie, Matthew, to Mr. Bliss, Surgeon, Hampstead [England], 18-- November 7 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 11)
  Letter from Matthew Baillie to Dr. Bliss requesting a description of the symptoms of a patient for a friend who wished to publish an account of the case. The letter includes a reply by Bliss in which the symptoms and account of the illness are described.
  Purchased from Hamill de Barkes, June 1962.
- Barbauld, Mrs. Anna Letitia, S. Newington, England, to Mrs. Carr, 1803 December 28 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 12)
  Letter from Mrs. Barbauld to Mrs. Carr confirming a visit for two or three days. Letter was removed from John Fulton's copy of Memoirs of Mrs. Barbauld (London, 1874).
- Beddoes, Thomas, 2 letters, no date and 1802 October 21 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 13)
  Letters of Thomas Beddoes to an unnamed physician, n.d., and to Dr. Currie, Liverpool, 1802 October 21, discussing medical cases and praising Erasmus Darwin's Zoonomia. Letters purchased by John Fulton from Myers & Co. and donated, February 1957.
- Beddoes, Thomas, [Bristol], to Mr. Phillips, London, 1806 April 15 (Box 1 A-F, Folder 14)
  Letter of Thomas Beddoes to Mr. Phillips discussing his own illness. Letter has the stamp of the Bristol Post Office. Donated before April 1948, probably by Arnold C. Klebs.
- Bernard, Claude, Paris, to the Dean of the Faculté de Médecin, Paris, 1854 July 8 (Box 1 A-F)
  His children are sick with scarlet fever and he excuses himself from leaving Paris to go to Douai.
- Bigelow, S. J. [?], Paris, to J. Mason Warren, Boston, 1873 November 30 (Box 1 A-F)
  Bigelow's mother is in Paris and suffering from tuberculosis. He requested that his mother consult Warren who was studying abroad at the time.
- Blackwell, Elizabeth, [New York], to Katie, [1851?] September 13 (Box 1 A-F)
  Elizabeth Blackwell received her medical degree from Geneva Medical College in 1849. She then traveled to England and France to continue her study of medicine, returning to New York in August 1851. The letter, written to her "very dear friend" Katie who is otherwise unidentified, mentions her recent return after two years' absence and her wish to renew their friendship.
- Blair, William, [London], to W. Bedwell [London], 1804 April 17 (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter from William Blair to W. Bedwell asking him for further information on the accusation he had made to the Royal Jennerian Society against Dr. Walker. Dr. Walker had been acquitted by the Society. Dr. Walker was presumably John Walker, Secretary of the Royal Jennerian Society. Letter was purchased from Old Hickory Bookshop (Acc. 25714).
- Blumer, George, correspondence with Abraham Flexner and others, 1918-1920 (Box 1 A-F)
  On setting up the full-time plan at Yale with money from the Rockefeller Foundation. Blumer was Dean of the Yale School of Medicine from 1910 to 1920. Folder also includes Blumer to John Fulton, 1951 April 10, Blumer to Ira V. Hiscock, 1958 April 22, and a reprint by Blumer, "Brief Recollections of the Yale Medical School (1906-1920)," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 21[5] (May 1949): 365-376.
- Blumenbach, Johann Friedrich, Gottingen, to ?, 1814 October (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter may be incomplete as there is no salutation. Recipient name is illegible.
- Boerhaave, Herman, Leiden, to "Mijn heere", 1734 February 3 (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter from Boerhaave to an unnamed recipient thanking him and praising him for a book he has written. With the letter is an unrelated envelope with seal in Boerhaave's hand addressed to a student named Outhuis. Letter (and envelope) purchased by John F. Fulton from Pierre Beres, Inc., Paris, 1947. Correspondence concerning the purchase is included in the file.
- Boyle, Robert, to "Madam", 1649 March 26 (Box 1 A-F)
  According to the book dealer's description, the letter asks a "Lady" to intercede with the French Ambassador to procure him a passport. Apparently after the execution of Charles I and the beginning of the Civil War, Boyle wanted to leave the country. Letter was probably obtained for the Library by John Fulton. The Library owned the letter before 1962.
- Bright, Richard, [London], to John Bostock, 1835 March 6 (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter from Richard Bright to John Bostock thanking him for his complimentary dedication in a recent publication. Dr. John Bostock dedicated his Sketch of the History of Medicin e (1835) to Richard Bright. The letter was the gift of Dr. Richard Hunter to John F. Fulton, 1956.
- Bright, Richard, to Dr. Maclaggin, 1850 November 17 (Box 1 A-F)
  Brief letter from Richard Bright to Dr. Maclaggan asking him to write. Sent to John Fulton by E. Weil, May 1949.
- Brown-Séquard, Charles Edouard, [Paris], to "Cher Monsieur", 1886 June 18 (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter of Charles Edouard Brown-Séquard to an unnamed gentleman discussing the votes lined up for him for a major election, presumably to membership in the Académie des Sciences. Brown-Séquard was elected to the Académie in 1886. A typed Engish translation of the letter is available. Letter purchased from Old Hickory Booksellers, 1957.
- Brown-Séquard, Charles Edouard, New Brunswick, N.J., 2 letters to Dr. Bache, Jr. [Thomas Hewson Bache], 1857 May 11 - 1857 May 18 (Box 1 A-F)
  The first letter concerns a possible exchange of journal volumes. The second requests a reference to obtain the chair of physiology at the future Cooper Union for the Advancement of Sciences and Art (founded in 1859). The letters were purchased from Argosy Books.
- Burggraeve, Ad[olphe], Gand, [Belgium], to [Jean-Baptiste] Nothomb, Ministre de l'Interieur, 1841 July 28 (Box 1 A-F)
- Butler, John Simpkins, Hartford, to L. Tupper, Esq., 1865 March 30 (Box 1 A-F)
  John S. Butler, a graduate of Yale College in 1825, was Superintendent of the Connecticut Retreat for the Insane. The letter discusses the "hard case" of Ellen O'Brien who is unlikely to improve.
- Buttner, Jacques L., Les Boyers, France, to Dr. Scobie[?], 1961 May 28 (Box 1 A-F)
  Jacques L. Buttner graduated from Yale School of Medicine in 1909. He discusses in his letter the good luck that brought him to Yale and how he decided to become a doctor, and what has since happened. He also mentions Horace Fletcher and discusses diet. The recipient appears to be a fellow alumnus, possibly Russell B. Scobie who graduated from the Medical School in 1929.
  Madeline Stanton noted that the letter was brought to the Library by Dr. Arthur Ebbert.
- Callow, W. J., Liverpool, to Sir Astley Cooper [London], 1840 August 16 (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter from W. J. Callow to Astley Cooper on a case of a dislocated humerus that he treated and for which the patient also consulted Cooper and a bone setter. Cooper's reply is written on the letter. Purchased by Harvey Cushing from Maggs Brothers, London.
- Canning, Edward, to Rev. Josiah W. Canning, Gill, Mass., 1848 February 21 (Box 1 A-F)
  Letter from Edward W. B. Canning to his father, Rev. Josiah W. Canning, on the birth of his child using ether anesthesia and on family matters. Letter is headed "Bulletin No. 2." Purchased by John F. Fulton from Symmachus Trading Company, Boston, June 1952.
- Cardwell, P. H., Knoxville, Tenn., to E. E. Miller, agreement for dental training, 1875 May 17 (Box 1 A-F)
  E. E. Miller will be admitted for three months to the dental practice of "Dr. P. H. Cardwell" for instruction and access to books and instruments for the fee of $50.
- Carmalt, William H., Rainsford Island Hospital, Boston, to "Dear Sir", 1859 March 10 (Box 1 A-F)
  Lengthy account of an unusual gynecological and obstetrical case. Carmalt later became professor of surgery at Yale.
- Chambers, William Frederick, to Dear Sir, no date (Box 1 A-F)
  Short note saying that he can't see the patient until 4:00 the next day. With this is a cut fragment with signature from a letter to a Mr. Miller. Gift of L. Cohen, Argosy, 1952.
- Chapman, Nathaniel, [Philadelphia], reference for his former student Dr. Martin, 1825 July 22 (Box 1 A-F)
  Dr. Martin had studied medicine under Chapman and had graduated at the last commencement of the University of Pennsylvania where Chapman served as a professor.
- Charcot, [Jean Baptiste August Etienne], Paris, to "Cher Monsieur" (Box 1 A-F)
  Madeline Stanton thought the author was the son of Jean Martin Charcot. Gift of H. W. Liebert, March 1957, in memory of C. C. Fry.
- Charcot, Jean Martin, Paris, to "Cher collegue et ami", no date (Box 1 A-F)
  Charcot asked that the recipient be extremely indulgent to young Vigues who is undergoing his examinations. He is the son of a good friend. Letter was the gift of John Fulton, 1959.
- Charcot, Jean Martin, Paris, note to B. W. Austen [?], 1893 August 13 (Box 1 A-F)